Faris B. Mismar

(214) 912 3263 Plano, TX 75025 https://www.linkedin.com/in/farismismar faris.mismar@ieee.org

Business Development and Solutions Director

An accomplished leader with 14+ years of experience in telecommunications and two years of experience in machine learning in creating and delivering solutions. Excellent project leadership and communication skills leading projects and teams of different sizes and backgrounds. Proven track of interfacing with executives.

Core Competencies: Project Leadership ■ Innovation ■ Presentation Skills ■ Conflict Management ■ Problem Solving ■ Machine Learning ■ Internet of Things ■ 3gpp RAN specifications.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

ERICSSON, Plano, TX Solutions Manager II – RAN and Machine Learning

2009-2017

2015-2017

- Served as machine learning authority role at Ericsson, Business Area Digital Transformation.
- Provided sales support for customers both in North America and around the globe. Examples of involved verticals: energy controllers, transport and logistics, and telcos.
- Developed machine learning algorithms (supervised and unsupervised) to create actionable insights for several high visibility customer use cases. Use cases spanned traditional telecommunication cases, end-user experience, and IoT.
- Designed and built an engine for predictive data analytics using machine learning for several operators and enterprise customers using Python (including scikit-learn, Keras (with both Theano and TensorFlow backends), and other packages), SAS, MATLAB, R, Alteryx, and KNIME. The development takes place on highly scalable environments (e.g., Pentaho connecting to Hadoop (HBase and Impala) and Azure).
- Delivered presentations in several Ericsson workshops held globally for machine learning (algorithms, platforms, and XaaS).
- Key contributor to the Ericsson v Apple global patent litigation (UMTS and LTE radio access standards). Press release on Dec 21, 2015 has settlement details.

Solutions Manager II – RAN

2013-2015

- Interfaced with CTOs and CTO teams from several customers and CUs on NDO topics.
- Functioned as technology authority for new technology introductions: eMBMS (NPO in Netherlands) and 5G (NR) testbed (AT&T).
- Led the Outdoor Heterogeneous Networks Experts Forum global initiative (15 members).
- Performed Customer Solutions role in a very high visibility LTE KPI RFP response acceptance, and contract negotiation (NDO) in Indonesia (XL Axiata) to improve Ericsson's O2C process efficiency without compromising on the LTE network quality.
- Authored an internal process document which helped win and deliver the service of identifying businesses closest to strands for a leading multi-system operator (MSO) as part of their public Wi-Fi hotspot deployment plan.
- Operated as a Consultant for the solution on Heterogeneous Networks strategic planning and design (NDO) to C-suite customers in Australia (VHA) and Saudi Arabia (Mobily).
- Performed SON-OM KPI analysis and reporting to Verizon for a 10 MHz LTE cluster on 700 MHz and AWS bands.
- Generated sales leads and performed sales support (costing and pricing and presentations).
- Engaged as a speaker in several global knowledge sharing events (Centra sessions).

- Delivered training for in-building solutions design using iBwave and capacity dimensioning for HSPA+ and LTE in many countries: USA, Spain, Australia, and India.
- Spoke in several workshops held globally for heterogeneous networks (products, services, and pre-sales).

Solutions Architect III - RAN

2011-2013

- Certified senior member of Competence Domain RAN, Network Design and Optimization (NDO) Global Competence Hub, Global Services.
- Executed Customer Solutions Responsible (CSR) role for one small-track project with SaskTel Canada.
- Consulted with operators on LTE spectrum bidding (700 MHz vs 2600 MHz).
- Identified and qualified sales opportunities.
- Performed RF capacity planning and forecast for LTE (including VoLTE), HSPA+, and Wi-Fi.
- Developed small cells strategy and planning for AT&T.
- Conducted technical pre-sales customer engagements with AT&T and other accounts.
- Led global teams of varying seniority levels, backgrounds, geographical locations, and cultures.
- Authored technical guidelines and white papers on small cells, connected devices, and smartphones.
- Tuned and optimized an LTE cluster (10 MHz; 700 MHz and 2100 MHz) in AT&T.
- Participated as a speaker in global and regional knowledge sharing events.
- Generated sales leads.
- Subject Matter Expert and Business Builder for Ericsson in Mobile World Congress 2013.

RF Services Engineer IV

2009-2011

- Facilitated the Stay Green initiative as the Regional Lead.
- Interfaced with AT&T executives and market managers on special events.
- Led the RF design for the Dallas Cowboys Stadium for AT&T HSPA+ radio coverage.
- Collaborated with AT&T Labs on WCDMA RF capacity modeling.
- Led a team to help improve an internal trace analysis tool.
- Led pre-sales effort for high-profile projects.

Free Lancing Consultant

2008-2009

At Ericsson:

• South East regional lead for the Go to Green NPI initiative. I worked on improving AT&T CQI KPI metrics on retainability, accessibility, IRAT, ISDR, and 3G on 2G. (Hired through Networkers International MSB).

At AT&T:

- Assisted the AT&T market team in Seattle, WA in answering to the regional and national teams.
- Implemented engineering designs to double the cellular capacity of the network as a result of the iPhone 3G launch. (Hired through LCC International Inc).

MOTOROLA, Middle East (Jordan, Kuwait, Saudi Arabia) RAN Professional Services Manager

2004-2008 2007-2008

- Achieved improved KPIs through RF optimization for Zain.
- Handled end-to-end investigation for deteriorated circuit and packet switching user experience.
- \bullet Implemented 3G/HSPA VIP call trace and analysis.
- Drove the effort to improve the most vital and important coverage areas.

UTRAN Services Team Leader

2006-2007

- Configured RNC5000 (Huawei RAN) with minimal 3PV support and launched it.
- Designed and implemented Iub, Iur, and Iu interfaces (IP and ATM).
- Planned and executed O&M IP network and the corresponding VLAN tagging.
- Engineered QoS parameters for IP Iub and Dual Stack Iub.
- Configured and administered OMC-U running on Solaris.

Systems Engineer 2004-2005

- Structured and tested softswitching, VoIP media gateways, and HSS for roaming in Jordan (Fastlink).
- Performed UNIX administration and shell scripting.

EDUCATION

The University of Texas at Austin, Austin, Texas, USA

Ph.D. in Electrical and Computer Engineering (DICE), Machine Learning and Internet of Things, December 2019 (expected).

The University of Texas at Dallas, Richardson, Texas, USA

Professional MBA, Organizations, Strategy, and International Management, GPA: 4.000 out of 4.000. Graduated with High Distinction.

The University of Texas at Dallas, Richardson, Texas, USA

Master of Science in Electrical Engineering, Concentration in Communications, GPA: 4.000 out of 4.000.

The University of Jordan, Amman, Jordan

BSc. in Computer Engineering, GPA: 3.78 out of 4.00. Ranked number 1 in class.

ADDENDUM

SOFT-SKILLS TRAININGS

Project Leadership, Management, and Communication • Finance for Non-Finance Managers • Presentation Skills • Negotiation Skills and Conflict Management • Project Steering • Leadership Core Curriculum for Individual Contributors • Consultation Core Curriculum • SPIN 2.0 • Toastmasters International Competent Leader and Competent Communicator • Onboarding for Sales.

LANGUAGES

English (Fluent), Arabic (Native), Spanish (Intermediate).

PLATFORMS AND COMPUTER LANGUAGES

Mac OS X (Darwin), iOS, Solaris, Microsoft Windows, C, C++, MATLAB, Python, R

HONORS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

Senior IEEE member since August 2017 • Marcus Wallenberg Foundation Scholarship for Scientific Research and Education, 2016, 2017 • UT Dallas Dean's Excellence Scholarship for Continuing Graduate Students Award, 2013-2014 • Toastmasters International Competent Communicator, November 2013 • Toastmasters International Competent Leader, July 2013 • Ericsson Key Contributor Award presented by Ericsson's former CEO Hans Vestberg, 2013 • UT Dallas SOM Dean's Excellence Scholarship Award, 2012-2013 • Motorola BRAVO! Awards for Q1 2007, Q4 2007, and Q3 2008 • The University of Jordan: Board of Trustees Award for Academic Excellence, 2004.

PATENTS AND PEER-REVIEWED ARTICLES

- F. B. Mismar and S. Nammi, "METHODS FOR ADAPTING A REPORTING PERIOD FOR A USER EQUIP-MENT," U.S. Patent: US 20160277256 A1, issued September 2016.
- F. B. Mismar and S. Nammi, "A METHOD TO TRANSMIT SIGNALING RADIO BEARER MESSAGES IN MULTI ANTENNA WIRELESS SYSTEMS," U.S. Patent: US 20160278119 A1, issued September 2016.
- F. B. Mismar and B. L. Evans, "Machine Learning Approach to Estimating mmWave Signal Measurements During Handover," *IEEE Wireless Communication Letters, submitted*, arXiv:1710.01879, October 2017.
- F. B. Mismar and B. L. Evans, "Improving Downlink Coordinated Multipoint Performance in Heterogeneous Networks," *IEEE Journal on Selected Topics in Signal Processing, submitted*, arXiv:1707.03269, June 2017.
- F. B. Mismar and B. L. Evans, "Deep Reinforcement Learning for Improving Downlink mmWave Communication Performance," *IEEE Journal on Selected Topics in Signal Processing, submitted*, arXiv:1707.02329, June 2017.
- I. Da Silva, Y. Wang, F. B. Mismar, and W. Su, "Event-based Performance Monitoring for Inter-System Cell Reselection: A SON Enabler," *International Symposium on Wireless Communication Systems*, Paris, Aug 2012.

Volunteering Experience

- Classical Arabic linguist and editor-in-chief for K-12 curriculum (al-Jadeed Arabic Language Series اللغة العربية): a series of textbooks for non-native Arabic language speakers in the USA. I am currently working on grades 1 through 5. My contributions are: content (poetry for children), proofreading, grammatical checking, and editorial changes.
- Google Translate: Level 22 Contributor in English-Arabic translation. Level 22 Contributor in Arabic-English translation. Level 2 Contributor in Spanish-Arabic translations (Google stopped this branch for contributions).
- Wikipedia: I have contributed to contents related to cellular communication, radio access protocols, and mathematics. In Classical Arabic, my contributions are mostly proofreading and editing to ensure that the content continues to preserve the endangered language.